Finding aid for the R.B. Kitaj papers LSC.1741
UCLA Library Special Collections
R.B. Kitaj papers
1950-2007 (bulk 1965-2006)
1965-2006
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kitaj, R.B.
LSC.1741
80 Linear Feet (160 boxes, 85 oversize boxes)
R.B. Kitaj was an influential and controversial American artist who lived in London for much of his life. He is the creator of many major works including; The Ohio Gang (1964), The Autumn of Central Paris (after Walter Benjamin) 1972-3; If Not, Not (1975-76) and Cecil Court, London W.C.2. (The Refugees) (1983-4). Throughout his artistic career, Kitaj drew inspiration from history, literature and his personal life. His circle of friends included philosophers, writers, poets, filmmakers, and other artists, many of whom he painted. Kitaj also received a number of honorary doctorates and awards including the Golden Lion for Painting at the XLVI Venice Biennale (1995). He was inducted into the American Academy of Arts and Letters (1982) and the Royal Academy of Arts (1985). He is the author of two books, The First Diasporist Manifesto (1989) and Second Diasporist Manifesto (2007). Kitaj's works are in the permanent collections of over 50 museums internationally.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of R.B. Kitaj, 2006, 2007, 2008.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9955983393606533
Biography
R.B. Kitaj was born Ronald Brooks, in Cleveland Ohio, on October 29, 1932 to Jeanne Brooks and Sigmund Benway. His parents divorced when he was two years old and the he had no further contact with his father who died in Los Angeles, California in the late 1940s. Jeanne Brooks supported herself and young Kitaj by working as a secretary at a steel mill. Kitaj's first art training came in the form of children's art school classes at the Cleveland Museum where he spent his Saturdays, while his mother worked. Ronald grew up in an agnostic, liberal home influenced by his mother's circle of friends, some of whom had fled the rise of Nazism in Europe. In 1941, Jeanne married Viennese refugee and research chemist, Walter Kitaj. Ronald adopted his stepfather's surname. In 1942, the family moved to Troy, New York where Kitaj attended Troy High School and developed lifelong friendships with Jim Whiton, John and David Ward and others. At the end of the World War II, Walter Kitaj's mother Helene came to live with the family in New York. Helene had fled Vienna in the 1930s and survived the Holocaust by taking refuge in Sweden while many of her family members, including two sisters, had been killed. Helene's presence had a strong impact on young Kitaj and also helped to form a distinct part of his Jewish identity. In one of his early works, The Murder of Rosa Luxemburg (1960) Kitaj depicts Helene along with his maternal grandmother, Rose Brooks.
In 1949, at the age of 17, Kitaj left Troy for the first of many voyages as a merchant seaman. Between jobs, Kitaj attended art school at the Cooper Union where he studied under the artist Sydney Delevante. In 1951, Kitaj made his first trip to Europe. Encouraged by his grandmother Helene, Kitaj visited Austria and enrolled in the Akademie der Bildenden Künste, Vienna. While studying in Vienna, Kitaj met his first wife, and fellow American, Elsi Roessler. They were married in 1953 in New York's oldest Methodist chapel. That winter, the newly-wed couple made a first of many visits to San Feliu de Guíxols in Catalonia, Spain. Years later, Kitaj bought a house in San Feliu where he spent several summers along the Catalan coast, painting and meeting with his good friend Josep Vicente Roma.
In 1956, Kitaj was conscripted to the U.S. Army serving first at Darmstadt, Germany, then as an illustrator in Fontainebleau, France. After completing his military service, Kitaj, inspired by the many American artists and writers who had expatriated to London before him, enrolled in the Ruskin School of Art at Oxford with support from the G.I. Bill. Kitaj sold his first painting from this period to philosopher friend John Searle. In 1959, his first son Lem Kitaj (screenwriter Lem Dobbs) was born. From 1959 to 1961 Kitaj attended the Royal College of Art (RCA) where he studied under Carel Weight, Roger de Grey, and David Sylvester. Kitaj befriended several classmates Adrian Berg, Peter Phillips, Allen Jones and David Hockney, who became a lifelong friend. Key paintings of the RCA years include: The Murder of Rosa Luxemburg (1960), Kennst du das Land? (1962), and Reflections on Violence (1962). Kitaj's first solo exhibition, Pictures with Commentary, Pictures without Commentary was held at the Marlborough Gallery in 1963. In 1964, Kitaj and Elsi adopted a daughter, Dominie Kitaj.
Between 1962 and 1969, Kitaj taught at Ealing Art College, Camberwell College of Arts, The Slade School of Fine Art, and University of California, Berkeley. In 1969, Kitaj's first wife Elsi committed suicide. Kitaj took his family to Saskatchewan, Canada to recover while he taught at the Emma Lake Workshops. In 1970, they returned to California where he taught for a year at UCLA. While living in Los Angeles Kitaj befriended the photographer Lee Friedlander and first met fellow artist, Sandra Fisher. Upon returning to London, Kitaj and Sandra Fisher met again at the opening of the Neal Street Restaurant in 1971. This chance encounter marked the beginning of their relationship of more than twenty years.
In 1975, Kitaj was asked by the Arts Council of Great Britain to curate an exhibition he named, "The Human Clay." The exhibition took place at the Hayward Gallery. In the introductory text of the catalogue Kitaj coined the term "School of London" to describe the group of artists, that he was a part of, working in London at the time, with a focus on drawing from and representing the human form. Some key paintings during this time include: The Arabist (1975-76), The Orientalist (1975-1976), The Hispanicist (1977-1978), Smyrnka Greek (1976-77), From London (James Joll and John Golding) (1975-76), The Neo-cubist (1976 -87) as well as numerous figurative pastel and charcoal drawings.
In 1981, the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden held the first retrospective of Kitaj's work. In that same year, Kitaj moved to Paris for a year with Sandra Fisher to work. In Paris he developed a close friendship with Avigdor Arikha and his wife Anne Atik. Upon returning to London Kitaj and Sandra Fisher were married by Rabbi Abraham Levy at London's oldest synagogue, Bevis Marks. Several important friends were in attendance including David Hockney, Frank Auerbach, Lucian Freud, and Leon Kossoff. Max Kitaj was born a year later in 1984. During this time, his work began to focus on the Holocaust, "The Jewish Question" and Kitaj's exploration of Jewish identity. Key works on these themes include, The Jew, Etc. (1976-1979), The Jewish School (Drawing a Golem) (1980), Self-Portrait as a Woman (1984), Germania (The Tunnel) (1985), and The Jewish Rider (1984-1985). In 1989, Thames Hudson published Kitaj's first book, "First Diasporist Manifesto." In the same year that his "First Diasporist Manifesto" was released, Kitaj suffered a heart attack.
Kitaj was asked by the Tate Gallery to do a major retrospective of his work just as his painting life had begun to slow down. Kitaj's retrospective was scheduled to tour two other museums, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and the Metropolitan Museum in New York. In 1994, when the exhibition premiered it was extremely well attended, but ultimately disparaged by the critics. Kitaj believed that British anti-Semitism fueled the negative reviews. After the exhibition closed at the Tate, Kitaj's wife Sandra Fisher died suddenly of brain aneurysm. Although Kitaj received an outpouring of support from friends and strangers alike, he vowed never to paint again, claiming both publically that the stress of the Tate show had caused Sandra's death. He came to refer to this period as his "Tate War," a battle that fueled his work in the following years. Regardless of the major set-back this time posed for Kitaj, he was still well received by the public. In 1996 he received the Wollaston Award for the best painting in the Summer Exhibition at The Royal Academy of Arts for his work "The Critic Kills." Kitaj also received other prestigious awards before leaving England for good in 1997, The Golden Lion for Painting (1995) and the Chevalier des Arts et des Lettres presented to him by Jacques Chirac (1996).
When Kitaj returned to the United States with his son Max, he bought a house in Westwood near UCLA, where he built a yellow studio. In 2001, Kitaj accepted the National Gallery of London's invitation to mount an exhibition of his work, Kitaj: In the Aura of Cezanne and Other Masters, his largest single exhibition. In Los Angeles, Kitaj focused on the development of what he called his "old-age style" which continued to reflect a variety of interests, including his life-long obsession with Cezanne, "The Jewish Question", and the untimely death of his wife Sandra Fisher. Some important works from this time include two series; the Los Angeles Pictures and Little Pictures. In 2007, Yale University Press published Kitaj's "Second Diasporist Manifesto." In October of 2007, Kitaj died in his home just weeks before his 75th birthday. Kitaj's last exhibition, "R.B. Kitaj: Little Pictures" was held in 2008 at the Marlborough Gallery, New York.
Exhibitions
Portrait of a Jewish Artist: R.B. Kitaj in Text and Image, January - April 2008. Held in conjunction with the Skirball Cultural Center's R.B. Kitaj: Passion and Memory.
Scope and Content
The contents of the R.B. Kitaj Papers give insight into the private and working life of the artist across several decades. It includes personal and business correspondence, writings by and about Kitaj, the artist's studio materials and art sources, research materials, publicity materials, drafts and proofs for several publications, photographs and other collected mementos and ephemera. Of particular interest are Kitaj's autobiographical writings, correspondence with individuals such as David Hockney, Lee Friedlander, Peter Blake, Frank Aurback, and Phillip Roth, napkin sketches, and A Day Book–a collaboration between Kitaj and Robert Creeley.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Academies, 1983-2006
Materials Created By R.B. Kitaj, 1978-2006
Writings
Sketches
Artworks
Writings about R.B. Kitaj, 1980-2002
Biographies
Interviews
Writings on R.B. Kitaj
Publicity, 1963-2006
Exhibits
Awards
Personal Objects and Memorabilia, 1975-2003
Personal Documents
Collected Objects and Materials
Photographs
Family and Friends
Materials Collected by R.B. Kitaj, 1984-2003
Invitations
Art Exhibits, Catalogs, and Posters
Art Bulletins
Works by Others
Photographs
Miscellaneous, 1980-2000
Personal Correspondence, 1951-2006
Business Correspondence, 1957-2006
Judaica
Tate Materials
Art Sources
Studio Materials
Cezanne
Photographs
Audio Visual Materials
Cassette tape
Compact disc
Videotapes
Related Material
Sandra Fisher papers (Collection 1870). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Artists -- United States -- Archives.; Kitaj, R. B.--Archives.
- 1. Academies, 1979-2007; 36 folders.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of materials related to the membership of various art academies. Academies include: American Academy of Arts and Letters, Royal Academy of Art, National Academy of Design, and American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Materials include: letters, publications, meeting minutes, candidate ballots,
  - No Subseries assigned
    - Academy of Arts, Berlin--exhibition invitations, 1995 - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters -- assorted materials, 1982 May 28 - 2006 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters --ceremonial programs, 1983 - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters -- death notices, 1983 - 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters -- member directories, 2004 - 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters -- Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences -- assorted materials, 1998 - 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Assorted ballots, CVs, and candidate descriptions (1 of 2), 1983 - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Assorted ballots, CVs, and candidate descriptions (2 of 2), 1983 - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - National Academy of Design -- assorted materials, 1983 - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- assorted materials (1 of 3), 1984 - 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- assorted materials (2 of 3), 1999 - 2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- assorted materials (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- death announcements, 1984 - 2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- invitations (1 of 2), 1984 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- invitations (2 of 2), 1984 - 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- Royal Academy Illustrated, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- meeting minutes (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- meeting minutes (2 of 2), 2005 January 18 - 2006 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- Summer Exhibition publications, 1992, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- Summer Exhibition publications, 2005, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Royal Academy of Art -- A Vision of Burlington Gardens publication, 1996 December 9 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Accademia delle Arti del Disegno, 1979 - 1995, 2001 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Akademie der Künste (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1981 - 2007 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1986 - 2007 (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1986 - 2007 (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - National Academy of Design (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - Royal Academy -- correspondence, 1976 - 1989 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Royal Academy -- correspondence, 1990 - 2007 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Royal Academy -- invitations, 1975 - 2007 (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - Royal Academy -- meeting minutes, 1971 - 1989 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Royal Academy -- meeting minutes (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Royal Academy Magazine, 1986 - 2007 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Biographies, undated (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Biographies, undated (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Biographies, undated (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Royal College of Art: One Hundred & Fifty Years of Art & Design, 1987 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - RCA Painting 1986: A Commemorative Issue (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - Royal Academy invitations, 2000 - 2006 (Box 130, Folder 26)
- 2. Materials Created by R.B. Kitaj, 1959-2007; 17 boxes
  This series consists of works by various artists, poets, and writers including printed materials, exhibit catalogs, posters and invitations.
  - No Subseries assigned
    - Batting for Dukakis -- Campaign materials, 1988 (Box 135, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified slide and print, undated (Box 138, Folder 18)
    - List of works -- Collection R.B. Kitaj: Own Pictures (Frames), undated (Box 138, Folder 30)
  - Artworks
    - A Day Book, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Rampant Lions Press, 1981 (Box 117, Folder 9)
    - Kaddish (1 of 2), 1992 (Box 127, Folder 16)
    - Kaddish (2 of 2), undated (Box 127, Folder 17)
    - Time Magazine, 28 November 1983 (Box 132, Folder 29)
    - Face Dances -- The Who (Box 132, Folder 30)
    - The Jerusalem Center for the Visual Arts, 1987 (Box 132, Folder 36)
    - Time Magazine cover -- proof, 1983 (Box 132, Folder 41)
    - Gustav Mahler -- portrait commission, 1997 (Box 135, Folder 29)
    - Speciman Musings of a Democrat, undated (Box 138, Folder 17)
    - Now Was and Is -- photograph of triptych (Box 138, Folder 19)
    - Isaiah -- zinc plate etching, undated (Box 148, Folder 2)
    - Time Magazine -- covers, 1986 (Box 150, Folder 19)
    - Book and magazine covers -- artwork by Kitaj, 1981 - 1995 (Box 153, Folder 9)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (1 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 6)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (2 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 7)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (3 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 8)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (4 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 9)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (5 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 10)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (6 of 15), Undated. (Box 163, Folder 11)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (7 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 1)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (8 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 2)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (9 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 3)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (10 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 4)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (11 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 5)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (12 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 6)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (13 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 7)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (14 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 8)
    - Day Book by Robert Creeley/Plates by R.B. Kitaj -- proofs (15 of 15), Undated. (Box 164, Folder 9)
    - Who's Next -- album cover draft, 1980 (Box 165, Folder 11)
    - Duncan and Dorn, NY, 1982 (Box 166, Folder 6)
    - "Horizon/blitz" -- pastel on canvas, undated (Box 166, Folder 7)
    - Marynka Smoking -- proof, undated (Box 187, Folder 3)
    - Jewish Art -- collage mounted on wood block, undated; 1 item. (Box 241)
    - Walter Benjamin poster, Undated. (Box 243, Folder 2)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Drawing 1896, oil on canvas 16 1/8 x 9 1/4 x 3/4 inches (Box 244)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Writing 1985, oil on canvas 18 1/4 x 10 10 1/4 x 1 1/4 inches (Box 244)
    - PASSION (1940 -45): Two Plumes 1985, oil on canvas 12 3/8 x 8 7/8 x 3/4 inches (Box 245)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Cross and Chimney 1985, oil on canvas 16 1/2 x 10 7/8 x 3/4 inches (Box 245)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Girl / Plume 1985, oil on canvas 22 1/4 x 8 7/8 x 3/4 inches (Box 246)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Landscape / Chamber 1985, oil on canvas 10 7/8 x 20 1/4 x 3/4 inches (Box 246)
    - PASSION (1940 - 45): Reading 1985, oil on canvas 18 1/8 x 20 1/8 x 3/4 inches (Box 247)
    - PASSION (1940 -45): Devotion / The Children (After Georges De La Tour), 1985, oil on canvas with mixed media 30 1/2 x 19 x 1 inches (Box 247)
    - ID (Three Famous Jews) 2004, oil on canvas 36 x 36 x 2 1/2 inches (Box 248)
    - EGO (Three Famous Jews) 2004, oil on canvas 36 x 36 x 2 1/2 inches (File 249)
    - SUPEREGO (three Famous Jews) 2004 (Box 250)
    - STUDY FOR THE 2nd DIASPORIST MANIFESTO 1970-1996, Mixed media collage 30 3/8 x 22 1/2 x 1 1/4 inches (Box 251)
  - Exhibits
    - Hirshhorn retrospective exhibition materials (1 of 3), 1978 - 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Gallery photographs, 1985 October (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Hirshhorn retrospective exhibition materials (3 of 3), 1978 - 1981 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Interviews
    - Unidentified essay, undated (Box 119, Folder 15)
  - Sketches
    - Sketches (1 of 2), no date (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Sketches (2 of 2), no date (Box 38, Folder 1-9)
  - Writings
    - Confessions draft (1 of 4), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Confessions draft (2 of 4), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Confessions draft (3 of 4), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Confessions draft (4 of 4), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Confessions materials (1 of 3 ), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Confessions materials (2 of 3 ), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Confessions materials (3 of 3), 2003 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Journals (1 and 2 of 4) (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Journals (3 of 4), ca. 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Journals (4 of 4), ca. 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous materials (1 of 4), ca. 1985 - 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous materials (2 of 4), ca. 1985 - 1989 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous materials (3 of 4) (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous materials (4 of 4), ca. 1986 - 2003 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Painting prefaces layout, ca. 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Responses to clippings, 1980 - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (1 of 6), ca. 2003 - 2005 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (2 of 6) (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (3 of 6), ca. 2003 - 2005 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (4 of 6), ca. 2003 - 2005 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (5 of 6), ca. 2003 - 2005 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Second Diasporist Manifesto materials (6 of 6), ca. 2003 - 2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - USC lecture (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Francis Bacon trial witness statement, 2000 -2001 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Notebook 1, ca. 1980 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Art Notes, undated (Box 115, Folder 1)
    - Jewish Art-Indictment and Defense: A Personal Testimony by R.B. Kitaj, undated (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - "Reflections on Violence", undated (Box 118, Folder 1)
    - "Waldheim/Vienna", 1986 (Box 118, Folder 2)
    - Art Sources/Notes, undated (Box 118, Folder 3)
    - Germania/Genesis of a Painting, undated (Box 118, Folder 4)
    - Germania, undated (Box 118, Folder 5)
    - Art notebook (Box 118, Folder 6)
    - Art notebook, undated (Box 118, Folder 7)
    - Art journal -- "Quotes", undated (Box 118, Folder 8)
    - Art journal -- "Old Pics", undated (Box 118, Folder 9)
    - "Passion" (1 of 4), 1965, 1985 - 1986 (Box 118, Folder 10)
    - "Inventory: The Story So Far" (Box 118, Folder 11)
    - Untitled essay, undated (Box 118, Folder 12)
    - "Tate War (I Accuse!)", undated (Box 118, Folder 13)
    - Tate War -- drafts (1 of 2), undated (Box 118, Folder 14)
    - Tate War -- drafts (2 of 2), undated (Box 118, Folder 15)
    - Paris Journal (Box 118, Folder 16)
    - French notebooks, undated (Box 118, Folder 17)
    - Essay for Modern Painters, undated (Box 118, Folder 18)
    - Art Notes, undated (Box 118, Folder 19)
    - Yellow notepad, undated (Box 118, Folder 20)
    - Loose pages (Box 118, Folder 21)
    - Ryman exercise book, undated (Box 118, Folder 22)
    - Yellow notepad, undated (Box 118, Folder 23)
    - Yellow notepad, undated (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - Yellow notepad, undated (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - Yellow notepad (Box 119, Folder 3)
    - "A Passion" -- drafts, undated (Box 119, Folder 4)
    - Essay on Degas -- drafts, undated (Box 119, Folder 5)
    - Essay on Young Contemporaries -- drafts, 1986 (Box 119, Folder 6)
    - Essay on Peter de Francia -- draft, undated (Box 119, Folder 7)
    - "Painting" -- draft (Box 119, Folder 8)
    - Essay on Jess -- drafts, undated (Box 119, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified lecture -- draft, undated (Box 119, Folder 11)
    - Still in Praise of Still Photography -- drafts (1 of 2), ca. 1985 (Box 119, Folder 12)
    - Still in Praise of Still Photography -- drafts (2 of 2), ca. 1985 (Box 119, Folder 13)
    - "After Duncan" -- draft, 1982 (Box 119, Folder 14)